Guide to the Atwater Family Papers, 1843 - 1943
Atwater Family Papers, 1843 - 1943
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Atwater family.
1000-145
3.5
7
The Atwater family included Wilbur O. Atwater, Wesleyan alumnus and professor, and his wife, Marcia Woodard Atwater. They had two children: Helen Woodard Atwater, a home economist and Charles Woodard Atwater, a lawyer.
The Atwater Family Papers contain the publications, personal papers and letters of members of Wilbur Olin Atwater's family. The collection centers around Wilbur Olin Atwater, Marcia Atwater (his wife), William Atwater (his father), Helen Atwater (his daughter) and Charles Atwater (his son). The majority of the collection is composed of letters written and received by the aforementioned people. They primarily discuss familial, financial or personal matters; with the exception of the papers of Helen Atwater, for whom there is a significant collection of papers and publications relating to her work in the field of Home Economics. The correspondence centers on family topics; current events are rarely discussed in the letters.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions
Acquisitions Information
Given by Mrs. John Kenneth Galbraith (Wilbur O. Atwater's granddaughter) in 1966.
Biographical Note
Wilbur O. Atwater (May 3, 1844-Sept. 22, 1907) was born the son of Minister William Atwater and Eliza Barnes Atwater in the small town of Johnsburg, New York. After growing up in Vermont and spending his first two years of college at the University of Vermont, he transferred to Wesleyan University and received his BA in 1865. He went on to receive his M.A. (1868) and Ph.D. (1869) from Yale University, studying agricultural chemistry; he later obtained his LL. D. from the University of Vermont (1904). A world-renowned chemist, particularly in agricultural chemistry, he is best known for his role in the development of the Calorimeter, which enabled the calculation of caloric content in food items. In 1874 he married Marcia Woodard; they had two children, Helen Woodard and Charles Woodard. He became a Professor at Wesleyan University in 1873 and he remained at the post until his death in 1907.
Helen Woodard Atwater (May 29, 1876-1947) was born in Somerville, Massachusetts to Wilbur Olin Atwater and Marcia Woodard Atwater. She received her B.A. from Smith College, a graduate of the class of 1897. She then became an editorial assistant to her father, which entailed preparing his material for publications. The experience provided her with an expansive knowledge of issues of nutrition as well as the opportunity to publish some of her own popular work on the subject. In 1909 she went on to spend the next fourteen years working as a scientific consultant for the Office of Home Economics in the United State Department of Agriculture; she wrote and edited bulletins relating to food, nutrition and other issues of home economics. During World War I she was placed on the Women's Committee of the Council of National Defense as the Executive Chairman of Food Production and Home Economics. When she left the Department in 1923, she joined the American Home Economics Association in Washington, D.C., becoming the first full-time editor of their official publication, The Journal of Home Economics. The Journal was a prestigious publication dealing with issues in the growing field of Home Economics. Through her position in the Association she was able to shape the organization's policies and image. She remained with the Association for 18 years; during that time she held various positions, including secretary of the International Committee and alternate for the Women's Joint Congressional Committee, of which she was Chairman for two years. Furthermore, as a member of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, she worked with the President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership. She was a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and was extended honorary membership to Phi Upsilon Omicron and Omicron Nu. She passed away in 1947 having never married.
Charles Woodard Atwater (April 23, 1885-March 24, 1946) was the son of Wilbur Olin Atwater and Marcia Woodard Atwater, born nine years junior to his sister Helen Woodard. He graduated from Wesleyan University in 1906 with a Ph. B. and Honors for general scholarship. He then went on to spend the next three years getting his law degree at Harvard Law School. In 1910 he moved to New York and began his law career; three years later he established his own law firm, Atwater and Clarke. From 1918-1919 he served as the Attorney General for the Southern District of New York. He also served as honorary consul and honorary consul general for Siam (Thailand) beginning in 1924. Charles married Alice Caroline Merriam on October 7, 1911. Together they had three children, Catherine Merriam (b. 1913), Robert Merriam (b. 1916) and Charles Woodard (b. 1920).
Collection Overview
The Atwater Family Papers contain the publications, personal papers and letters of members of Wilbur Olin Atwater's family. The collection centers around Wilbur Olin Atwater, Marcia Atwater (his wife), William Atwater (his father), Helen Atwater (his daughter) and Charles Atwater (his son). The majority of the collection is composed of letters written and received by the aforementioned people. They primarily discuss familial, financial or personal matters; with the exception of the papers of Helen Atwater, for whom there are is significant collection of papers and publications relating to her work in the field of Home Economics. The correspondence centers on family topics; current events are rarely discussed in the letters.
Collection Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically by name.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Atwater family.; Atwater, W. O. (Wilbur Olin), 1844-1907.; Atwater, Charles Woodard, 1885-1946.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Alumni and alumnae.; Home economics--United States--History--20th century.; Atwater, Helen W.; Atwater, Marcia Woodard.
Related Material
Wilbur Olin Atwater Papers, 1876-1903, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Vertical File on Wilbur Olin Atwater, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wilbur Olin Atwater Papers, 1869 - [circa 1914], Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library: http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/EAD/htmldocs/RMM02223.html
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Betsy Atwater
  Grandmother of Wilbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters from her to son William, 1843, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Charles Atwater
  - Letters from him to his parents, 1891-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from him to his parents, 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from him to his parents, 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from him to Alice Merriam, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from him to family (summer and law school at Harvard), 1906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from him to Mother and Helen, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from him to Alice Merriam, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters from him to Alice Merriam, January 1909 - December 1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from him to Alice Merriam from Europe, June 1909 - July 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from him re: law practice in NY, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from him to Alice Merriam, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters from him to Alice Merriam, 1911 (later his wife) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters from him to family, 1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters from him to daughter, Catherine, 1915-1922 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters from him to wife, 1916-1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters to him from various people, 1898-1923 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters from him to others, 1925-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Cousins, Aunts, Uncles, and Brother-in-law
  - Letters from them to WOA (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Eliza Barnes Atwater
  Mother of Wilbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters to WOA, 1864-1868 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Eliza Barnes Atwater, 1865 - 1868 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Florence Atwater
  Sister of Wilbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters from Florance Atwater to WOA (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Aunt Harriet
  Aunt of Wilbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters from Aunt Harriet to WOA, 1882 - 1893 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Helen Atwater
  - Letters from Helen Atwater to her parents, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Helen Atwater to brother, Charles Atwater, 1908-1916 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Helen Atwater, 1904-1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Biography (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Journal of Home Economics and Smith College Alumnae (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes on the evolution of table manners (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Helen Atwater - Speeches and Articles (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
- L. R. Atwater
  Uncle of Willbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters from him to WOA, 1881-1891 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Marcia Woodard Atwater
  Wife of Willbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters to her husband, 1874-1904 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Letters to her from her friends on engagement to WOA, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Letters to her from Father, Abram Woodard, 1869 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1875 copy of will of Sarah Woodward Sargent (Sister of Marcia) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Letters from nephew of niece (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Letters from her to her parents from Europe, 1882-1883 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters to her from Professor Francis G. Benedict, 1904 - 1905 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Letter from her to Mr. True regarding her husband's illness, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Letters to her about illness of her husband, 1904-1907 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Letters of condolence on death of WOA, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Letters and cards of condolence on death of WOA, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Recipe book, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Letters from her to her children 1895, 1906 - 1922 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Wilbur O. Atwater
  - Pocket diary, 1867 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letters to him from friends and classmates, 1860-1869 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding first jobs, 1871-1873 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pocket diary, 1875 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pocket diary, 1876 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Pocket diary and pocket notebook, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Two pocket notebooks, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Letters to his wife, Marcia, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Letters to his children, 1892-1898, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Letters from him to various people, 1873-1901 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Letters to his wife, Marcia 1893-1901 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Letters from and to him during illness, 1904-1907 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - 1907 obituaries (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Papers concerning disposal of his library, 1907-1908 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Family correspondence, 1875-1909 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Financial records, etc., 1870-1911 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and notes about biography of WOA, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- William Atwater
  Father of Wilbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters to his father and mother, Thomas and Betsy Atwater, 1844 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Will (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Temperance papers (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Textbook, 1850-1852 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Original poems and clippings, 1836-1869 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Account book, 1851-1882 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Letters to WOA, 1863 - 1875 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Letters to and from others regarding WOA invention of substitute for slate pencils, 1871-1877 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Estate - Difficulty of settlement 1891-1909 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Letter to Lawyer from WOA's sister Florence (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Mary Barnes
  Maternal grandmother of Wilbur O. Atwater.
  - Letters from her to WOA, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Laura Arabella Waldo
  Belle - Sister of Wilbur O. Atwater
  - Letters from her to WOA, 1862-1863 (Box 7, Folder 14)